Guide to the Lathrop C. and Mabel H. Urner Harper Photograph Collection ca. 1872-1954, n.d (Bulk 1891-1934) PR 121
New-York Historical Society
Lathrop C. and Mabel H. Urner Harper Photograph Collection
[1872]-1954, undated (Bulk 1891-1934)
New-York Historical Society
Harper, Lathrop Colgate, 1867-1950
PR 121
3.6 Linear feet (6 boxes)
Collection of personal photographs of Mabel Herbert Urner and Lathrop Colgate Harper, their extended family, their Gramercy Park home and their extended vacations to Europe. Publicity photographs taken for Mabel Urner's newspaper column are included.
Provenance
Gift of the Estate of Lathrop Colgate Harper on December 23, 1957.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Biographical Note
Lathrop Colgate Harper (1867-1950) and Mabel H. Urner Harper (1881-1957), a socially prominent couple of early twentieth-century New York, lived for years on Gramercy Park and served as benefactors for some of New York's finest institutions. Their domestic lives and European travels were immortalized in the pages of over one hundred newspapers in the United States, Canada and Great Britain through Mabel Urner's syndicated, semi-autobiographical column, The Married Life of Helen and Warren.
Lathrop Colgate Harper was a successful rare book dealer, consultant to many major U.S. research libraries and authority on incunabula, Americana, and medieval manuscripts. A native New Yorker, Harper traced his lineage to several distinguished New York families. His grandfather, Samuel Barker Harper (b. 1777), married Christina Arcularius, daughter of New York Alderman and State Assemblyman Philip J. Arcularius. Harper's father, the tea merchant James Philip Harper, married Margaret Perego, daughter of a wealthy New York merchant whose family had settled in New Jersey by 1750. Harper was the great nephew of New York Mayor James Harper and second cousin of the Harper Brothers publishers.
In 1887 Harper joined his elder brother, Francis P. Harper, in the rare book business at 4 Barclay Street. The bookstore successively moved to 17 East 16th Street, 14 West 22nd Street, 437 Fifth Avenue and finally 8 West 40th Street. After his brother's early retirement in 1910, Harper developed his interest in Americana.. He became a much sought-after source of rare Americana after obtaining for William L. Clements the Americana library of Newbold Edgar, which would become the core collection for the William L. Clements Library at the University of Michigan. He was granted an honorary Master of Arts by the University of Michigan in 1928 in honor of his efforts in the library's development and subsequent growth. He was well known to many research libraries, serving on library committees for Harvard University, Princeton University, The New-York Historical Society and the Council of The Bibliographic Society of America, among others. In the 1920s, he developed an interest in incunabula (books printed before 1501) and went on to compile the first catalogue of incunabula published in the United States, A Selection of Incunabula Describing One Thousand Books Printed in the XVth Century (New York: 1930), once considered a basic reference resource.
In 1912, Indiana native Mabel Herbert Urner (1881-1957) married Lathrop C. Harper. She continued to use her maiden name in her professional life. She began a newspaper column in 1914, The Married Life of Helen and Warren, a fictional account that was based primarily on her life with Harper. The column was eventually syndicated in over 100 newspapers in the United States, Canada and Great Britain; it ran for thirty years, finally ceasing in 1944. The couple took yearly trips to Europe, during which Harper hunted for rare books and Urner combed markets for seventeenth and eighteenth century samplers, antique glassware, antique snuff tins, amber, furniture and other collectibles. Harper became known as a connoisseur and keen appraiser of rare books, and Urner developed collections to fill their Gramercy Park home that would eventually catch the eye of the national press and be bequeathed to the Metropolitan Museum of Art after her death. Her readers' queries about the couple's travels and interest in the cuisines of Europe eventually prompted Urner to write and self-publish a series of noncommercial but popular "Guidelets" on European travel and food, beginning in 1930.
In 1948, just two years before his death, Harper received an honorary Doctor of Arts degree from Brown University. The citation acclaimed his achievements and industry in helping to compile libraries across the nation, stating, "The shelves of the noblest libraries in this country reflect your zeal for letters and your discriminating love of books." He died in his office on August 11, 1950, his hand still holding the phone as he prepared to make his nightly call to his wife. Urner followed him in death on March 2, 1957, leaving behind thirty years of journalistic writing. Parts of the Harper estate were donated to New York area institutions including Princeton University, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and The New-York Historical Society.
Scope and Content Note
The Lathrop C. and Mabel H. Urner Harper Photograph Collection spans the period from 1872-1954, with many undated materials. The collection consists of 3.6 linear feet of black and white photographic prints, tintypes, film negatives, glass negatives, and drawings. The photographs mainly relate to the personal and family life of the Harpers, with a few photographs relating to Lathrop C. Harper's rare book shop. Also included are some of Mabel H. Urner's newspaper column publicity photographs. The collection includes documentation of some of the couple's yearly tours of Europe prior to World War II.
Arrangement
Photographs are arranged alphabetically by geographic name or name of sitter.
Materials have been arranged into the following series:
Missing Title
Series I: Buildings
Series II: People
Series III: Vacations
Series IV:Negatives
Related Material The New-York Historical Society
The Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections holds other images related to this collection.The Album File (PR 002) includes more Harper, Perego, Arcularius and Dimmock family photographs, some of which are duplicates of those in this collection. The Cased Photograph file (PR 012) contains additional photographs of Harper, Perego and Arcularius family members. For written materials on both Lathrop C. Harper and Mabel H. Urner Harper, see the New-York Historical Society Library's Lathrop Colgate Harper Papers and the Collection of clippings, manuscripts, articles, etc. relating to Lathrop Colgate Harper.
Tintypes (prints); Portraits.; Glass negatives.; Europe -- Description and travel -- Pictorial works.; Gramercy Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Booksellers; Women journalists -- New York (State) -- New York; Antiquarian booksellers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Drawings (visual works); Arcularius, Andrew; Bachrach, Fabian, 1917-2010; Beals, Jessie Tarbox; Budd, Emma; Davis & Sanford; Hargrave & Gubelman; Harper family; Harper, Althea M.; Harper, Christine A.; Harper, Ella Adelaide; Harper, Francis P.; Harper, James P.; Harper, Margaret Perego; Hewitt, Mattie Edwards, 1869-1956; Lathrop C. Harper, Inc.; Lewis, R. A. (Photographer); Parsonage, Douglas; Perego, Francis Ella Brennan; Perego, Ira; Underwood & Underwood; Urner, Mabel Herbert, 1881-1957; Wroth, Lawrence C. (Lawrence Counselman), 1884-1970
- Series I: Buildings
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I contains exterior and interior views of the residences and businesses of the Harpers and their extended family. The series contains some photographs from 1895, but most are undated. Files are arranged alphabetically by type of building. Included are several prints of the bookstore run by Lathrop C. Harper and his brother, Francis P. Harper, including one undated print by Long & Heppner of Francis Harper in the interior of the store when it was located at 17 West 16th Street in New York City, one unattributed 7 x 10 ink drawing of the store's interior, and a few photographs of Lathrop's clerk and successor Douglas Parsonage. The Harper's residences at 36 Gramercy Park and 1 Lexington Avenue on Gramercy Park are captured in a series of photographs of both the interior and exterior, at least one of which was published in House Beautiful in March 1924. Included are several interior photographs, some taken by Mattie Edwards Hewitt, of the Harpers' home which document their collections of historic European samplers, antique furniture and family portraits. Also included with the residence photographs are two photographs of 193 10th Street, Lathrop Harper's parents' residence from 1854-59. The photographs of the fire at the store of Ira Perego, Harper's maternal grandfather, show New York City police and firemen at work in a smoke-filled street. The unidentified buildings are primarily residential, with one photograph of an unidentified Yacht Club included. Some related negatives can be found in Series IV. Oversize images are in Box 6.
  - Bookstores of Lathrop and Francis Harper, 1895, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Residences of Lathrop and Mabel Urner Harper, some by Mattie Edwards Hewitt, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Store of Ira Perego, fire, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified Buildings, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: People
  Series II consists mainly of portraits of the Harpers and their close relatives, dating from 1872-1954, with many undated photographic prints. Photographs are arranged alphabetically by sitter with unidentified individuals at the end. Thereunder photographs are arranged chronologically when dates are available and alphabetically by description when dates are unavailable. Highlights include publicity portraits of Mabel Herbert Urner Harper, notably those by Jessie Tarbox Beals. Many portraits of Mabel and Lathrop were taken in their victorian home or outdoors in Gramercy Park. The family portraits focus mainly on Lathrop Harper's siblings: Ella Adelaide Harper, an amateur writer; Christina A. Harper (whose sketches of her mother are included with her mother's portraits); Francis P. Harper, his business partner; and James P. Harper, Jr., a prominent diamond importer. One of the photographs of James P. Harper, Jr. was originally framed; the frame was separated from the photograph during processing and can be found in Box 5. There is one folder of group portraits of the family. Also well documented is Lathrop's mother, Margaret Perego Harper. There are a few photographs of other members of the Arcularius, Perego, and Dimmock families for whom the familial connection is unclear. Photographers represented in this series include Jessie Tarbox Beals, R.A. Lewis, C.D. Fredricks, R. Horton, Fabian Bachrach, Davis & Sanford, Underwood & Underwood and Hargrave & Gubelman. Related negatives can be found in Series IV.
  - Arcularius, Andrew, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Budd, Emma Jourdan, 1907, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dimmock, Andrew and Selina Harper, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Harper Family, group portraits, some by R.A. Lewis, 1907-1912, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    General note
    See also: Box 5, Folder 85
  - Harper, Christina A., 1891, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Harper, Ella Adelaide, some by R.A. Lewis, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Harper, Ella Adelaide, some by R.A. Lewis, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Harper, Francis P.--Portraits, 1895-1900, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    See also: Box 1, folder 1
  - Harper, Francis P.--With Althea M. Harper in St. Petersburg, Florida, [1925-1938] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Harper, Francis P.--With Althea M. Harper, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Harper, James P., Jr.--Portraits, 1895, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Harper, James P., Jr.--Portraits, full length, 1889-1905, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    See also: Frame removed from portrait, Box 5, folder 106
  - Harper, James P., Jr.--Portraits, bust length, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
  - Harper, Mrs. James P., Jr., undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Harper, James P., Sr., by R. Horton, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Portraits, [1872] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Portraits, bust, 1888 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Portraits, 1897-1900 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Portraits, bust, 1912 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Miscellaneous, 1940, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Portrait in bookstore, 1948-1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
    See also: Box 1, folder 1 and Box 5, folder 87
  - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Brown University Commencement, with Lawrence C. Wroth, 1948 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
    See also: Box 5, folder 56
  - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Portrait, bust by Fabian Bachrach, 1948 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Passport photographs, 1949 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Harper, Lathrop Colgate, with Mabel Herbert Urner Harper, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Childhood Photographs, [1881-1900] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portrait by Underwood & Underwood, with photograph of a drawing made from portrait, 1914 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Seated at desk, 1914 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portrait, full length, 1917 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 33)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portrait at residence, by Davis & Sanford, 1923 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 34)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portrait at door of 1 Lexington Avenue, by Jessie Tarbox Beals, 1926 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 35)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--In residence and Gramercy Park, 1939, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 36)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--At The New-York Historical Society, 1954 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 37)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--In Gramercy Park, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Headshots, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 39)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Passport Photographs, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 41)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portrait, full length by Underwood & Underwood, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 42)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portraits by Pan-American Photo Service, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 43)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portraits, seated at desk, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 44)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portraits, seated at round table, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 45)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portrait, seated with book, by Davis & Sanford, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 46)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portrait, seated with cat, by Underwood & Underwood, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 47)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portrait with horse, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 48)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portrait with horse, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 49)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--At residence, with fireplace and collection cabinet, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 50)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--At Shelter Island, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 51)
  - Harper, Margaret Perego--Portrait in garden, 1891 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 52)
  - Harper, Margaret Perego--In the Thousand Islands, 1895 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 53)
  - Harper, Margaret Perego--Portraits, 1897 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 54)
  - Harper, Margaret Perego--Portraits, 1902-1903 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 55)
  - Harper, Margaret Perego--Portraits, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 56)
  - Harper, Margaret Perego--Portraits and sketches by Christina A. Harper, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 57)
  - Perego, Francis Eliza Brennan--Photograph of painted portrait, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 58)
  - Sackett, Amanda, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 59)
  - Ramney, Francis P. and family, some by Hargrave & Gubelman, 1888, 1897, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 60)
  - Unidentified females, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 61)
  - Unidentified males and groups, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 62)
- Series III: Vacations
  Series III spans the dates ca. 1890-1938 and consists primarily of the Harpers' personal photographs from their yearly trips to Europe, the majority dating from the 1930s. Photographs are arranged alphabetically by country and thereunder by city. Unidentified locations are at the end. Related negatives are filed in Series IV, Box 5.They focus mainly on the couple, but do include pictures of the Caledonian Market in London and scenery from the cities of Germany, Italy, Switzerland and Austria prior to World War II. Also included are a few photographs of earlier family vacations in Atlantic City, the Catskill Mountains and the Thousand Islands. Negatives of varying sizes exist for many of the European trips and can be found in Series IV.
  - Austria--Vienna, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 63)
  - Czech Republic--Prague, 1931 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 64)
  - England--London, Caledonian Market, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 65)
    See also: Box 5, folders 92-94
  - France--Paris, 1932 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 66)
  - Germany -- Frankfurt, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 67)
    See also: Box 5, folder 95
  - Germany -- Heidelberg, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 68)
  - Germany -- Munich, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 69)
    See also: Box 5, folder 96
  - Germany--Miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 70)
    See also: Box 5, folders 97-99
  - Italy--Venice, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 71)
  - Italy--Miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 72)
    See also: Box 5, folder 100
  - Switzerland--Lugano, 1932 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 73)
    See also: Box 5, folders 101-102
  - United States--Atlantic City, NJ, [1905] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 74)
  - United States--Catskill Mountains, NY, [1895] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 75)
  - United States--Thousand Islands, NY, 1895 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 76)
  - Unidentified locations--family suitcases with travel stickers, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 77)
  - Unidentified locations--Hot air ballooning, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 78)
  - Unidentified locations--Miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 79)
  - Unidentified locations--Miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 80)
  - Unidentified locations--Waterscapes, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 81)
- Series IV: Negatives
  Series IV spans the dates 1934-1950, with many undated negatives, arranged into three subseries: Buildings, People and Vacations. There are approximately 200 negatives; some are 35mm, but most are a variety of sizes, with the smallest a glass negative measuring 2 x 2, and the largest a pair of identical glass and film negatives measuring 6 ½ x 8 ½. Most of the negatives correspond to photographs in Series I-III of this collection, but some have no corresponding prints. Many are unidentified.
  - Buildings
    - Residence of Lathrop C. Harper on Gramercy Park, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Residence of Lathrop C. Harper on Gramercy Park, undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Residence of James P. Harper, Sr. on 10th Street, undated (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - People
    - Harper family, group portraits, undated (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Brown University Commencement, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Harper, Lathrop Colgate--Portraits in office or bookstore, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portraits, undated (Box 5, Folder 88)
      See also: Box 5, folders 107-108
    - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portraits in Gramercy Park, undated (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portraits in residences, undated (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--Portrait, bust (glass negative, 2 x 2 in.), Undated (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Vacations
    - England--London, Caledonian Market, undated (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - England--London, Caledonian Market, undated (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - England--London, miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Germany--Frankfurt, undated (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Germany--Munich, undated (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Germany--Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 97-99)
    - Italy, undated (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Switzerland--Lugano, undated (Box 5, Folder 101-102)
    - Switzerland--Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Switzerland--Zurich(?), undated (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Unidentified locations, undated (Box 5, Folder 105)
- From Series II. People
  - Frame separated from Portrait of James P. Harper, Jr. in Box 1, folder 16, undated (Box 5, Folder 106)
- From Series IV. Negatives
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--film and glass negatives of portrait with horse, undated (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert Urner--35 mm negatives of portraits at 1 Lexington Avenue, undated (Box 5, Folder 108)
- From Series I. Buildings
  - Bookstore of Lathrop and Francis Harper, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 109)
  - Residence - 36 Gramercy Park - interior, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 110)
- From Series II. People
  - Harper, Francis P., undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 111)
  - Harper, Mabel H. Urner, 1921, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 112)